<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The French herald summoning all true Christian princes to a generall croisade, for a holy warr against the great enemy of Christendome, and all his slaues. Vpon the occasion of the most execrable murther of Henry the great. To the Prince.</title>
            <author>Loiseau de Tourval, Jean.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01260</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11374</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111986</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847245</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847245</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12271</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01260)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12271)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 729:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The French herald summoning all true Christian princes to a generall croisade, for a holy warr against the great enemy of Christendome, and all his slaues. Vpon the occasion of the most execrable murther of Henry the great. To the Prince.</title>
                  <author>Loiseau de Tourval, Jean.</author>
                  <author>Marcelline, George, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 49, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. Allde for Mathew Lownes, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Bishops head in Pauls Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed with a Maltese cross within a triangle, i.e. Jean Loiseau de Tourval.</note>
                  <note>Formerly attributed to George Marcelline.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Henry IV, 1589-1610 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12271:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12271:1"/>
            <p>THE FRENCH HERALD SVMMONING ALL TRVE Chriſtian Princes to a generall <hi>Croiſade,</hi> for a holy warr a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the great Enemy of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, and all his Slaues. VPON THE OCCASION OF the moſt execrable murther of HENRY the great. <hi>TO THE PRINCE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>E. Allde</hi> for <hi>Mathew Lownes,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the Biſhops head in Pauls Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, 1611.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12271:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12271:2"/>
            <head>TO THE PRINCE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Herald, whoſe very phraſe bewraies him enough to be french, though he neuer ſpoke his owne french yet; and who ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther choſe, vpon, ſo vrgent a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, to ſpeake ill &amp; in a ſtrange language, then not at all; now moſt rightly preſents himſelfe firſt vnto your highnes: becauſe aſwell by your merit, as by your fortune, you are one of the chiefeſt (if not euen the firſt) vpon whome he calls for the performance of the greateſt, moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian and moſt royall duty that euer was yeelded, to the greateſt perſon deceaſed, to the greateſt perſons li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. It is no leſſe then the cauſe of God, no leſſe then the cauſe of the Gods; ſeing, Princes are ſtiled ſo, by him that onely is ſo, and who, by a moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent faſhion, aboue all other men, after his owne Image made them ſo: And what a more godly ground for all Chriſtians to take the croſſe on them, againſt him that vnder a gawdy ſhow of many falſe croſſes, the more<pb facs="tcp:12271:3"/>croſsely becauſe cloſely, croſseth the onely and true Croſſe of Chriſt? Wherein, if it be not your ſelfe (vnder the happy auſpices of your glorious father, or rather hee himſelfe by you) then I ſee no <hi>Generall</hi> in the world, when our Chriſtian Army muſt come into the field. An other reaſon I haue more eſpecially and wholy to apply to your highnes, that which is intended to many; A moſt ſpeciall and holy zeale to your Princely ſeruice, which euen eight yeares agoe, brought me into your Country, and ſtill working in my hart, now enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces me rather to giue you a ſmall touch ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, how meane ſoeuer, then it ſhould be longer hid from you, how much I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>YOVR HIGHNES Moſt humble, moſt obedient, and moſt ready to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded ſeruaunt, <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12271:3"/>THE FRENCH HERALD Summoning all truly Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to a generall <hi>Croiſado,</hi> for a Holy VVarr, againſt the great Enemy of Chriſtendome, and all his Slaues.</head>
         <div type="section">
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho ſhall giue me an yron-voice, that I may ſound out to the foure cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners of the Earth the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt peece of infamy, the ſtrangeſt, the wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt treachery, the rareſt treaſon which euer was ſince the foundations of the world were laid? But alas! who will beleeue my report? And now to repeat that which the very Infamy thereof, long ſince hath made ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous through all Nations, Is it not in ſome ſort moſt needles? Oh that it were ſo! But ſince ſo great, ſo pregnant, ſo extraordinary a cauſe, hath not yet produced conformable effects; Needs, needs I muſt remember you, as though you knew<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12271:4"/>it not, or had forgotten it, That that King, that King of Fraunce, that great King of Fraunce, that mighty, that tryumphant, that victorious, that famous Monarch, that Thrice-great HENRY, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of his time, horror to his enemies, that faithfull one to his friends, is (alas ſhall I ſay is, when he is no more, or if he be yet, is nothing but a very nothing) dead, ô miſchiefe! twenty yeares before his time, in the ſtrength of his age, in the current of his glory, in the beginning of a new courſe for more &amp; more victories, in the very time when moſt we needed him. He is dead, but (<hi>ô</hi> Lord) how is he dead? It is a great thing when a King, euen a meane King, dyes; a thing that ſhakes often the deepeſt founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Kingdome, ſometimes of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours: a thing where of all the world will ſpeake &amp; thinke much, though dead euen leaſurely and by the ordinary way. But when a great King, and ſuch a great one as our great HENRY (If euer the like haue ben, or ſhall be) comes to an vntimely end, not by that eaſy courſe of Nature, but ſuddainly ſnatched &amp; violently plucked away from his owne, from the very armes of his owne, by the baſe &amp; deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perat attempt of a mad beaſt; who not able, not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to endure the beames of his royall face, giues him his death before from behind; It is a caſe ſo ſtrange, ſo rare, ſo vnheard of, that if there can be any ſuch wonder, it were onely not to wonder at it: and would to God we might paſſe no further. We wonder at the furious faſhion of Lyons, euen if tame, or when we looke vpon them thorow their grates; we wonder at the roaring of the waters euen<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12271:4"/>a farre off: But if we ſee them once let looſe, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged vpon vs, If the ſtreames ouerflowing their bankes haue once couered our champions, and we be caryed away by the currents, ſwimming between the apprehenſions of a weake hope and the pangs of a deadly Ship-wrack; Then leaue we wondring and begin fearing, by ſo much more fearfull as the former wonder was great and full of it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Who ſhall giue me an yron-voyce that I may thunder out, the moſt high, the moſt lamentable complaint that euer was heard in the world, ſince our loſſe is the greateſt that euer was in the world? Alas! not the Lyons, not the fierceſt beaſts of <hi>Affrick,</hi> but the infernall Furies, the enchained ſpirits of the bottomles pit, the Dogs, the Wolues, the Tygers, the Lyons, the Vipers, the Serpents, the Dragons of hell, are let looſe vpon vs, walke and wander a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, vnder the ſhape and name of French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to worke our miſchiefe; for french muſt needs be that hand that muſt kill Fraunce, though Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers thruſt it on: as though they could find no where els, ſo much boldnes, or ſo much deſperate wickednes. Alas! not one riuer, not many, but a whole Ocean of miſeries hath ouerwhelmed our whole land, now that royall mound, now that bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen wall, now that ſacred trench is broken; which with-held it from ſwelling againſt vs. What poore hope now (if feare may be ſo tearmed) but of a huge if not a generall flood of woes? Terror and death en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiron vs round about, which could not enter vpon vs but by that gap. And we are left ſwimming toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; among the direfulleſt monſters of the deepe<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12271:5"/>in ſuch a heauy caſe, as thoſe which the merciles, mouth of the ſea will ſpare, ſhall not eſcape their hungry bellies: And yet, French-men, there is a ſmall ſparke left vs, of a better hope, if we can be wiſe.</p>
            <p>Who ſhall giue me an yron-voyce that I may break into their minds, whoſe eares the ſound of my doleful co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint hath pierced? That I may ſtir them vp, no longer to a ſilent wonder, no longer to a mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting compaſſion; but to a bloody anger, and no leſſe pittiles then iuſt reuenge; of ſo wonderfull, ſo pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſo wrongfull a treaſon? The ſo miſerable loſſe I ſay, of ſo great a King; a loſſe, alas! I cannot ſay it enough, ſo great, ſo publick, ſo generall, ſo vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall, ſo farre and wide extending it ſelfe, euen to thoſe that thinke they haue no intereſt in it, euen to thoſe that beleeue they haue gayned by it, That we may boldly affirme, all the world, knowne and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne, ſubiects and ſtrangers, friends and foes, yea his greateſt enemies, and who ſo trecherouſly furthered his end; haue loſt in him: for where they thought to eſcape his victorious hands, which had no further end of Glory, then the ſweetnes of his wonted clemencie; they muſt needs fall into ours, who more fierce now then otherwiſe we had ben, not as a Lyoneſſe, not as a Tygreſſe, rob'd of their deere yong ones, but as deere children trayterouſly depriued of their deereſt father, will neuer graunt them that pardon, which they might eaſily haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained at his hands.</p>
            <p>Curſed, <hi>ô</hi> curſed and diſmall day, wherein we ſee the face of our Fraunce ſo ſorowful, ſo glad but the day before; our Queene ſo pittifully lamenting, the<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12271:5"/>day before ſo gloriouſly crowned; our Court ſo deepely mourning, the day before ſo highly reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing; wherein, <hi>ô</hi> miſchiefe, wee ſee a great King dead, which not onely the day before, but euen the ſame, and many after, made the furtheſt parts of <hi>Europe</hi> to tremble at his greatnes, that could not ſo diſtinctly haue heard the bruit of his fal. Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed once more, <hi>ô</hi> curſed, no more worthy to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led day, but black and diſmall night, where French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men loſt their King, Fraunce her father, the Church her ſonne, the Nobility their maiſter, the people their protector, the whole world his ornament; wherein the greateſt perſon of the world, was moſt vnluckily murthered by the leaſt, the beſt by the worſt, the moſt honored by the moſt infamous.</p>
            <p>And thou <hi>ô</hi> eternall ſtaine to the French name, ſcandall of mankinde, abhomination to the times, execrable Fury let out of hell to commit ſo haynous a parricide; remaine, <hi>ô</hi> ſempiternally remaine in the deepeſt of thy darke dungeon, thou incarnate diuell for euer and euer accurſed; And may thou neuer come out of thoſe flames wherein thou art ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruedly tormented, but only to receiue the laſt doome of thy euerlaſting and dreadfull damnation.</p>
            <p>But thou, oh my deere Country, heretofore ſo glorious, now a ſhamefull and bloody Stage of ſo pittifull a Tragedy, wilt thou euer be a fruitfull mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of trayterous King-killers? muſt cruell <hi>Affrica</hi> yeeld vnto thee both in quantity &amp; quality of mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, which now of late thou bringeſt forth, who neuer before didſt beare any? wilt thou neuer haue a King but with this prouiſo, thou ſhalt kill him<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12271:6"/>with a knife? Good Lord! what an ouerſight, what a blindnes in a Prince otherwiſe ſo ſharp-ſighted, to haue ſeen a like blow giuen to his next Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour, yea to haue receaued himſelfe another v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his owne face, beſides ſo many other deſperate attempts, which he might haue reckoned for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny warnings; and yet make no more vſe of other mens miſ-haps, nor of his owne feeling?</p>
            <p>The knife of that perfidious in-<hi>Clement</hi> (alas muſt I againe bring to memory thoſe ſacrilegious cay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifs?) was yet ſcarce dry from the blood of the laſt VALOIS, when that of deſperat
<hi>Chaſtell</hi> was dyed in the blood of the firſt BVRBON; &amp; the ſame was yet reaking hot, when this ſauadge Bedlem imbrued his in the beſt blood of his hart: Ah wretch! what haſt thou done? <hi>ô</hi> Guard where were you? French men whereof dreamed you? <hi>Creſus</hi> had but one ſon, and he dumbe, yet ſeing the life of his father in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daungered, hee could cry aloud <hi>Saue the King.</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture at that extremity vntyed the ſtrings of his tong; and a ſilly childes affection, ſtronger then the very deſtinies, could effect with a ſimple word, and againſt many, that which ſo many men, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny French-men (truly vnworthy of ſo great a Prince) could not with-ſtand, neither with tong nor hand, oppoſing themſelues againſt the weake attempt of one onely. And yet France lackes not a million of white ſoules, which would rather haue wiſhed that impious ſteele red-hot in their owne bowels. But no man can ſaue where God hath once decreed to deſtroy; and ſurely we muſt looke for no leſſe, ſince he hath taken to himſelf that valiaunt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>et,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12271:6"/>which was able to preuent our deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Celeſtiall gardians, and thou ô mighty Angell, which hadſt ſo happily led him through ſo many daungers, returned him victorious out of ſo many battells, why did yee not put by that blow, like the former? had yee ſo faithfully kept him hitherto, now to giue him ouer to the fury of this enraged beaſt? Lord! how the meaſure of our ſinnes muſt needs haue ben heaped vp and running ouer, ſince thou thoughtſt it fit to ſtrike vs with ſo mighty a thunderbolt of thine anger? Lord! how much is that man voyd of iudgement, who knowes not this to be a iudgement of thine owne, moſt iuſtly giuen out againſt the fulnes of our iniquities?</p>
            <p>Poore Prince! but more poore people! wee had ben ſo often threatned with a blow from heauen; now alas, now it is burſt out vpon our miſerable heads! who told it not, who heard it not, that thou ſhouldſt dye when thy Gallery ſhould be at an end? Who red not the to true and no leſſe vnhappy predictions, that expreſſely ſaid thou ſhouldſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue a wound behind? how many moſt vnfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, moſt vnlucky
<hi>Caſſandraes,</hi> had written vnto thee vpon the murther of thy predeceſſor, that thou mightſt take it as a looking-glaſſe and a leſſon; and the conſideration of his ſo vntimely death, might be the preſeruation of thine owne life? yet all that could not ſo worke, but that noble courage of thine, enemy to all miſtruſt, thine owne goodnes to-to acceſſible, thine owne eaſineſſe haue ben ſo many kniues to pierce thy boſome.</p>
            <p>If death had found this great king in his bed, and<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12271:7"/>by a naturall way, it is an ordinary thing, which ſcarce one would wonder at; If he had found it in a battaile, leaſt of all; for there euen moſt he ſought it, which then moſt fled before him: But to be murthered in his owne Paris, in his Caroche, in the midſt of his neereſt ſeruants &amp; by a baſe <hi>Pedant,</hi> not by one, but by two ſeueral wounds, with a ſhort knife (as though it had ben at his full choyce) It is ſo wonderful &amp; ſo prodigious an euent, &amp; ſo far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all likelyhood, that hitherto beliefe can ſcarce lay hold of it: me thinkes yet I am in a dreame, or for a while enchaunted when I remember it; and that mine eyes and eares (only deceaued for the time by ſome ſtrong illuſion) will preſently be freed of their error, and I ſhall ſee my King againe.</p>
            <p>How is ſo great a Monarch, the feare and terror of his Enemies, and who vpon the preparation of ſo great an Army held the whole world at a bay; How is ſo great a Monarch, paſſed euen in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from this world to another? He that had but the day before crowned his Queene! he that was the day after to lead her tryumphant into Paris! he that was immediatly to march forth with that fearefull Army, which threatned to ſtampe all his Enemies to pouder! Good Lord! how many high diſſignes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowne? how many threds cut with that of his life? and what a wretched <hi>Remora</hi> ſtaies now a great ſhip? He was ſo full of life and vigor, he had ſo many friends and ſo many meanes, ſo many men and ſo many horſes, ſo many armes and ſo many cannons, beſides ſo much courage and valour, ſo much iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and dexterity, ſo much reſolution and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12271:7"/>ſo much experience and readines, in warre, in ſtate, Campe, Counſell, and euery where; as it is vnpoſſible to diſcerne, whether he was more valiant or more wiſe, more polliticke or more mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, being a like excellent and perfect euery way. And all that could not helpe, but a forlorne wretch, a man of nothing, a nothing and not a man, hath ſtayed the courſe of ſo great, ſo mighty and ſo matchleſſe a Monarch, to whom euen the moſt dreadfull elements had yeelded, &amp; who ſent a trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Ague into the harts of all thoſe, who were conſcious to haue deſerued his anger.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Melun</hi> he ſhunned the attempt of <hi>Barriere;</hi> At
<hi>Fontainebleau</hi> that of a <hi>Spanyard,</hi> who would haue rewarded him with a trecherous death, euen when he healed him of the Kings euill: At
<hi>Paris</hi> that of a mad fellow yet liuing, and whom he would neuer ſuffer to be puniſhed, ſo naturally was he giuen to compaſſion and clemency. Al theſe attempts, thogh miſſing indeed, together with that which really, and effectually, did beat out his very teeth, were ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to prouide him againſt this laſt and fatall blow. But alas, that to braue minde could neuer learne how to feare. And yet the very day of his death, had he ſome ſecret feeling of his end; Hee laye downe twiſe or thriſe vpon his bed againſt his cuſtome, &amp; ryſing againe as oft, kneeled and prayed hartely to God that morning, as if he had foreknowne it would be his laſt.</p>
            <p>For that morning he was intreated not to ſtirre abroad, and fore-warned by a learned Aſtronomer, (called <hi>La Broſſe</hi>) that that day was dangerous to<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12271:8"/>him: but he, truſting his owne goodnes, and after ſo Chriſtian a preparation, reſolued to any thing his maker would lay vpon him, made ſo ſmall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thereof, as going after noone to the <hi>Arſenall,</hi> even he refuſed to take any Guard. Neuertheleſſe an hower before, he could not well frame with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, if he would goe or tarry; being deuided be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the with-drawing counſell of his good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, &amp; the impulſiue force of his deſtiny; a thing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vnvſuall to the promptnes of his wit, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer before hauing ben ſeen to ſtagger vpon any occaſion: At laſt his courage and our miſchance got the vpper hand. When he receaued the blow, he was reading a letter from the <hi>Arch-duke,</hi> who offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him paſſage for his Army, and to defray all charges through his Country; And in the very fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of his ioy, our ſorrow ouertooke him. Oh! how farre was he in the world when he went out of it? But ſure, thoſe cruell blowes were more againſt our ſelues then againſt him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and God in his wrath took that ineſtimable iewell from vs, whoſe worth wee neuer rightly valued. Yet O Lord, ſtay heere at the leaſt; we, indeed, are worthy of a ſharper puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but altogether vnable to beare it; Giue vs leaue now to lament for our worthy Prince, for whom forgiue vs, ô father, if perhaps our ſorrow be more then is due to any mortall.</p>
            <p>And yet, deere Country men, thus farre may we ioy in our ſorrow, and thanke God for many com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts which cannot eaſily be taken from vs; we ſuffer a great loſſe indeed, &amp; moſt ſenceles &amp; ſtony were we, if we ſhould not feele it; But, I pray you, looke<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12271:8"/>ouer me with mee, both the fortune and nature of our ſtate. Whenſoeuer any new line of our Kings hath ben about to ſet vp it ſelfe by his own ſtrength, theſe great changes haue neuer ben without great troubles, and ſome extraordinary great conuulſion: For as in the naturall, ſo in the Politicke body, as a chiefe bone cannot be broken without much vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, but when it comes once to knit againe, there growes a certaine hardnes &amp; calloſity, more ſtrong then euer the bone it ſelfe was: So, when after ſuch aebreach the Kingdome hath once taken root, &amp; ben well eſtabliſhed, the father euer left it ſurer to his fonne, and a fonne, greater then his father. aboue whome as <hi>per excellentiam,</hi> he alwaies got the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name of
<hi>great</hi> indeed. We had but three lines ſince our ſtories began to be written by our owne men; for in thoſe times our fore-fathers more carefull to do, then curious to ſpeake, rather gaue then tooke occaſion of writing: So that if euen thoſe, that moſt would haue concealed it, had not ben forced to tell it vs, we ſhould haue knowne nothing of our ſelues afore
<hi>Faramond.</hi> But looke how ſoone came in our firſt <hi>Clovis?</hi> but the ſecond after <hi>Merouee,</hi> from whom the firſt line tooke name; and how iuſtly deſerued he the ſurname of <hi>great;</hi> if in that golden age of ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity thoſe ſwollen titles had ben in vſe? And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward was not our <hi>Charles</hi> great indeed; the ſecond of the ſecond line, to which euen in double reſpect he gaue name? Now in the third, was not our <hi>Robert,</hi> both King and ſurnamed <hi>great,</hi> euen during his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers raigne, who (neuer ſo worthy) had but a ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſurname; as though his ſonne had ben the very<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12271:9"/>ſoule of the Kingdome, and the father could not truly be a King without him. And howſoeuer the acceſſion now of <hi>Bourbon</hi> to the Crowne, cannot rightly be tearmed the change of a line, no more then that of <hi>Valois</hi> (being iuſt both alike, after the ſucceſſiue deceaſe of three brethren, without heire male, ſucceſſiuely Kings after their father) but only the ingrafting of a natiue bud vpon his owne ſtock; yet the example may hold, becauſe it is a new branch and name: and more, eſpecially becauſe one braue Prince, was more ſtood againſt, more powerfully and more paſſionately, then euer any of all thoſe before, or euen all they together. He had wonderful ſmal meanes whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he came to the crown, and no better friend but <hi>Dieu &amp; ſon droit,</hi> with his owne ſword; he was of a religion contrary to that which was formerly profeſſed in his kingdome: he had not only the bodies, but, which is worſe, harts, mindes, and ſoules, ſtrongly preoccupated, &amp; who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bent againſt him: all which oppoſitions he muſt needs ouercome one by one: And howbeit in the end he ſetled his affaires, &amp; was a better Catholique then the Pope himſelf, yet the weake faith of ſome incredulous ſoules could not as yet well receaue it; and the wily craft of thoſe deceitful Foxes, or rather rauenous Wolues, accuſtomed to make aduantage <hi>as ill</hi> of ſilly mens weakenes, as of deſperate wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches reſolutions; and whoſe wide clawes nothing eſcapeth, be it neuer ſo hot or cold, light or heauy, diſſembling their owne knowledge, did foſter and further the others vnbeleefe, &amp; made away to make him away.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:12271:9"/>Yet his vertue &amp; ſtrength are not dead, but with a fame and a name which can neuer dye, and is able ſtil to win battels, as a new <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> after his own death, He hath left vs a ſucceſſor, who as another Phoenix ſweetly rayſed out of thoſe Aſhes, and ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vpon our darkned Horizon, as a new Sunne in his Oryent, faithfully promiſeth to dry our moyſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned eyes, and cleere vp all the miſts of our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes. And as a Great one ſaid once, ſince more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore the Sunne ryſing then declyning; no doubt but this new Planet, now ſo happily beginning to ſhine vpon our heauen, ſhall one day be ſaluted and worſhiped by many more ſubiects, then that whoſe courſe was of late ſo vnhappily ſhortned.</p>
            <p>And indeed, if we may iudge of the fruit by the flowers, his buds are ſo many, and ſo faire already, that when it ſhall once pleaſe God to ſpread them, they cannot but exceed the moſt perfect beauties, and euen the very Gold of his own Lillies. Nothing can be imagined greater then the motions of that yong Prince; and me thinkes I ſee already in him a picture in litle of that worth of his father, which doth promiſe, I know not how much, more in this hopeful abridgement then in the original: as though God reuiuing in him not only all thoſe former ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, would ad to his number ſome other more, as yet to the world vnknowne. It is wonderfull to ſee him at this age, ſend out ſo many liuely ſparkes of that powerfull <hi>Genius</hi> within him, ſaying already ſuch things, as would contend in excellency with all thoſe old ſayings of <hi>Plutarch;</hi> as though he would put to ſchoole againe thoſe famous men that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therd<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12271:10"/>them: taking it of the father as wel as his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domee. For who was there in the world more quick more ſharpe; and of a more preſent wit then he, who could put down at his pleaſure the moſt ſolid iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by the readines of his anſwers? This young ſonne of his is actiue, ſtirring, couragious, as he was; ſo delightfull, as one would neuer be weary to looke vpon him; Of ſuch a natural towardneſſe to al his exerciſes, as you would thinke Art can teach him no more; Of a man-like fairenes, and drawing already to be a man before mens expectation; through which manly lineaments yet ſhines a royal greatnes. It was a ſorowfull Eſſay, yet very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable to all his ſubiects in that publike deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to ſee his gratious faſhion at the Parliament, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the firſt time on his royall Throne of Iuſtice, aſſiſted with the Queene his Mother, Princes, Peeres and Officers of his Crowne; and to heare him ſpeak with ſuch a Maieſty as did gaine-ſay his Age, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-reach our reaſon: yet all that, nothing like to his faire preſence, to his royall countenance, at his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py coronation, as though moneths had ben yeares, for his prentiſhip, and he had perfectly learned to be a King, afore he be a man.</p>
            <p>He is carefully trayned vp, vnder the vigilant care of a wiſe mother, who could giue a good proofe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the brunt of this generall miſchance, and in euery action ſince, how well her great minde was fitted to the greatnes of her charge; And will not be leſſe bleſſed in the gouernment of this Empire, and in bringing vp our lawfull king in all vertues meet for his great rancke, then in the bringing him<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12271:10"/>into the light of this world: A Princeſſe indeed moſt accompliſhed in euery thing, and whoſe he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roycall quallities ſurmount the ordinary feeblenes of her ſex, beyond proportion.</p>
            <p>He is ſeconded with two young brethren, who as two ſtrong Pillars of the Realme, ſhall without wearynes faithfully lend their ſhoulders to the weight of his charge. He hath three faire Princeſſes to his Siſters, whoſe happy mariages wil ſtrengthen more and more the firmnes of his Scepter; Beſides ſo many great and ancient alliances of his fathers approued friends, whoſe only name will ſuffice to beate downe the power of ſuch enemies, as would riſe againſt him. He hath a mighty Army at hand at all times, many treaſures to maintaine it, and many braue Generalls to commaund it; which, like ſo many thunders, are ready to fall vpon all that would offend him. So that if any had but the leaſt knowne thought thereof, I do not ſay of his ſubiects onely, but euen among his greateſt Enemies, he ſhould ſooner be cruſhed with the force of the blow, then heare the noiſe of it.</p>
            <p>Away therefore, goe and hide your ſelues for ſhame, ye vaine bablers, blacke ſoules, infamous remnants of the League, infernal matches of our ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill fires, poyſoned ſprings of all our miſeries; be neuer ſeen, be neuer heard in the world with your Syren-Songs, that our enemies are moued with pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty through the ſtrange cruelty of our accident, and that although their hatred were yet in his heate, it will now be cooled in the depth of our miſchiefe; as though we were ready to call for their mercy, as
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12271:11"/>though it were in their hands to be good to vs, and feare had taken ſuch impreſſion in our harts, as France were glad to kneele to the next Conqueror. O God! what a baſe ſlackenes, what a fayned faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, what an open treaſon? &amp; yet you dare miſ-call it Policy and skill of State; Good Lord! what a hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Policy, to ſhow weakenes in this great body, where there is none? when rather (if there were any) it were true skill to conceale it. And how farr is that from emboldning vs, by the very weakenes of the enemy himſelfe; who by that vnhapy remedy wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he was conſtrained to put by for a time his euil to come, hath ſo baſely vncouered his ſhame, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayed the ſores of his eſtate? All their ſafetie was ſet vpon the point of a bad knife, which if it had miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed our Kings royall boſome, our ſwords could not haue miſſed their execrable breſts, vnleſſe they had preuented vs with cutting their owne filthy throats.</p>
            <p>O braue French-men, Thoſe that in the ſharpeſt of their ſickenes, in the extremity of their weaknes and irreſolution, carryed the fire and the ſword into the very hart of Cleue-land, brauely to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour their friends; ſhould they not be able in the beſt of their health, in the height of their ſtrength, and when the ſtate hath taken firme roote and forme; ſhould they not be able now more brauely to defend themſelues againſt their Enemies? Nay, but there is another reckoning to be made. If we may euer ſmel out, that this miſchieuous blow hath ben ſent vs by any one in the world, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the Eaſt, the Weſt, or the South, (the North we need not feare, it is to white and to pure<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12271:11"/>to vſe ſuch black remedies and hath no cauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) We muſt, we ought, and we will dye, men, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, children and all, in our reuenge; we will goe and fetch them downe from the very tops of their hills, ſearch them into the deepeſt holes of the earth, if they runne &amp; hide them-ſelues thither; wee will pul them out, to their deſerued ſlaughter: If not, we will rather deſtroy our whole ſeed, then leaue a generation which might remember and reproach to our taynted memory, that we were ſuch Traitors to our King &amp; to our ſelues, as to wincke at ſuch an iniury. For if we be ſo faint-harted, as to ſuffer thoſe attempts vpon our Princes, without making merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe vengeance, to light as quickly vpon the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors heads, we are gone for euer; there are no more French in Fraunce, no men, no Monarchy, none of that auncient freedome and franchiſe, from whence we deriue our name; there is no Fraunce in the world. They will boaſt we complaine, but dare not ſay who hath hurt vs. They will pronounce ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of death in their owne Chaires at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure againſt our deereſt Kings, they will ſend to kill them when they liſt, and all our ſtraighteſt guards, &amp; all the cruelleſt puniſhments we can inuent, ſhall not be able to keep them: For the earth will neuer ceaſe to bring forth murtherers, ſo long as it brings forth golde, or religious arguments; nor our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to ſet them againſt vs, ſo long as they ſtand in feare of our greatnes.</p>
            <p>What muſt we doe then in ſo lamentable a caſe? Take onely a fearfull puniſhment of that curſed cay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue? Make euen with the ground the infamous den<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12271:12"/>wherein he was borne; lay waſte the vnhappy ſoyle that brought him forth; cut downe the trees of ſo hurtful a ſhade; ſowe al the ground ouer with ſalt, &amp; leaue no re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nant, no memory of al that curſed brood, moſt iuſtly puniſhed, to haue any part in ſo porten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous a monſter. Alas! &amp; yet this hath not ben done; &amp; yet it were but a ſmall ſuplice, &amp; a ſory reuenge, farr farr inferiour, farr farr vnanſwerable to our great ruine: It were onely to whip the clothes, as the Perſians vſed, and to puniſh the inſtrument, without paſſing to the cauſe, as one that would breake the ſword and forgiue the murtherer. Doe you beleeue if we had ſpared him, he would euer haue refrained the like attempt, ſince euen amidſt the rack and tortures, and in the apprehenſion of a direfull death, he had ben ſo powerfully taught and perſwaded, as he ſtood faſt to his damned reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? what thinke you then of them that ſet him on worke, but that looſing ſuch an Inſtrument (as they were well content) their loſſe is ſo little, their profit ſo great, as they will euer moſt gladly venture like loſſes, for like gaines.</p>
            <p>Once more what muſt we do then? ſtay till that furious ſerpent, onely cut by the taile, returne more fierce then before, to ſprinckle our <hi>Louure</hi> afreſh with the blood of France? Ah! let vs rather dye, or bruiſe a thouſand times his miſchieuous head, then fall into the like extremity againe; and rather kill al in reuenge of the preſent outrage although there were none henceforth to be feared.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:12271:12"/>
            <p>SIR, I muſt needs ſpeak vnto you the firſt, though the youngeſt; you haue the firſt, the greateſt, and the neereſt intereſt in the quarrell: And I am your moſt humble and faithfull Subiect. Of al abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations in the world, treaſon is moſt to be abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; The king your father hath often ſeen al chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome wholy bent to his ruine, ready to ouerwhelme him; &amp; yet cold that neuer ſtop the current of his vict<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>orious fortune. But now as he was going, as a mighty whirl-wind to ouerthrow al his enemies, there he is ſtopt by one only Traytor; who ſhewed to truly (as
<hi>Auguſtus</hi> ſayd) that there is nothing ſo dangerous, as the reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a coward: A coward indeed, but ſuch a one as hauing no particular quarrell, that might caſt him into ſo high an extremity, muſt needs be mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued to it by ſome higher powers. If that may euer be found (Sir) &amp; if it were poſſible that the feeling loſſe of ſuch a Father (to whoſe bleſſed memory all your ſubiects dayly ſacrifice their deereſt teares, all your Allies their hotteſt ſighes, and generally all honeſt men their deepeſt mourning) could not moue you to take Armes againſt the Authors of our miſ-haps; the meere reputation of your kingdome, the ſafety of your owne life ought to do it: And let not the conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your vnder-age hinder ſo iuſt a war. Your own father ſcare exceeded your yeares, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he began to be a ſouldier; when both he and the Prince of
<hi>Condé,</hi> in regard of their youth, were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>the Pages of the Admirall.</hi> Do not venture your life in an imaginary peace, more then in open warr; your life, I ſay, no leſſe is the mark they aime at. The noble examples of your predeceſſors, yet recent and<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12271:13"/>before your eyes, the beſt hart-blood of your ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing father, yet hot-ſmoking vp to your owne no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrills, challengeth that duty of you.</p>
            <p>Open or ſuſpected Enemies, our Kings haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies laughed at; but ſecret and hidden ones euer made vs to weepe: and better it were to haue a mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion in an open battell before you, then one alone lurking in a corner. And better yet ſeeke a noble death in the midſt of all daungers, through a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſpeares and as many muskets, then dayly looke for it in feare and ſuſpition.</p>
            <p>Suſpition, Sir, is not the Element of the kings of France; They cannot be mued vp all day in their clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſets, without taking the aire but at a window, or ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king to their people through a reed; They cannot liue but free, euer abroad, euer on horſebacke; fighting is more pleaſing to them, and leſſe daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous then playing. They can dye in Tiltings, neuer in Battells; in their owne Citties, in their Chambers, &amp; with a violent death; neuer in warr, but by ſicknes or a naturall courſe. True it is, few kings dye in warr alſo, for few goe thither; but the kings of Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce haue ſought it in the remoteſt <hi>Affrick,</hi> carried it into the very hart of
<hi>Aſia,</hi> euer returning victorious, &amp; tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing ouer their vtmoſt extremities: while death durſt neuer be ſo bold as to aſſaile them but by the ordinary way. There haue ben ſome ſick, ſome priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ſome dead; Neuer any one killed, much leſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome; yet was it not for want of ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>turing throgh the hotteſt perills; Neuer any Princes went more freely, nor further into them: But it was, that they haue euer ben inuincible, and, as it were, immortal,<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12271:13"/>when they ſtood vpon their guard. But were it not ſo, and that our kings free and farre from all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt and harme, could liue altogether ſafe, and out of the ſhot of all trecherous deſignes; into what contempt, I pray you, wold fal the blood of France, in times paſt ſo honorable among all nations, if they ſhould but once ſee that it durſt not reuenge it ſelf againſt thoſe that cauſed it ſo trayterouſly to be ſhed? If this ſhould not nerely touch it, what would? &amp; what iniuries would it reuenge hereafter, if this were now ſo lightly paſſed ouer? would it not belye it ſelf, &amp; with it ſelf the publick voice of the world, afirming that neuer any offred it diſgrace or iniury, without deere repentance? And would it not harten his enemies, to continue their miſchieuous blowes, if they ſaw the whole vengeance light vpon one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the inferior and weaker inſtrument?</p>
            <p>Our King <hi>Frauncis</hi> the great, had no other ground for that bloudy warr he made againſt the Emperor, but only the reuenge of a ſeruant of his, <hi>Merueilles;</hi> The death of that man alone coſt the liues of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth thouſand, and ſhooke the very foundacions of Europe. And now ſhall the death of the greateſt king that euer wore the Crowne of France, be ſo meanely regarded, ſo ſlightly paſt ouer, euen by his owne feruants, by his owne ſonne; without more feeling, without more ſtirring, then for a glaſſe bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken? And ſhall all poſterity ſee the ſtory, &amp; our Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phewes read therein, without bluſhing at the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſibility of their Fathers? What would ſo many Nations ſay, which do ſo honorably eſteeme of the French name, if they ſhould ſee vs drinke vp ſuch a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12271:14"/>ſhame? What would we ſay, our ſelues, to the ſacred ghoſt of that famous Prince, if (as once that of <hi>Achil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> to the Greeks) it returned and would reproch vs, we ſacrificed nothing vpon his Tombe? Wil we ſay it is want of mony? The <hi>Baſtille</hi> is heaped full with it; want of men? Fraunce ouerfloweth with them; want of friends? Neuer any King had more or better; want of Armes and munition? Neuer ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe was better furniſhed, both for quantity and goodnes. What want wee then, but that rare King hath moſt aboundantly left it vs to reuenge his death?</p>
            <p>Ah, Sir, I can well tell what we want; nine or ten yeares more &amp; nothing els: &amp; you ſhould haue had them for vs, if that vnhappy wretch had not ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely preuented the natural death of your health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful father: But what? Did we neuer beat our Enemies, euen vnder yonger Kings then your ſelfe? what then vnder the infant <hi>Clotaire,</hi> whom our Queene his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther carried hanging on her breaſt, in his ſwadling bands, at the fore-front of the battell, crying aloud <hi>French-men, this is your King?</hi> She was a Queene in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and he a king neuertheleſſe, though young; nor thoſe olde French, daunted euer the more. And yet by the way, I would wiſh you to note, that this young King, this ſucking babe, being ſcarce foure moneths old when he wonne battells, was the firſt afterwards, who for his greatnes, valor, and worth, got the glorious ſurname of <hi>great</hi> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g his French, thogh yet in thoſe dayes of a general goodnes, they were more ready to nich-name their kings for one onely vice, then to honour them for many good<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12271:14"/>qualities; ſo rife were theſe, ſo ſcarce, thoſe. What? and vnder <hi>Lewis</hi> your owne Ancetor, whoſe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py name you carry, as well as his Scepter? Did not he ſucceed in this ſame State, and very neere at the ſelfe-ſame age as your ſelfe? And did he leaue to chaſtiſe his Enemies abroad, his rebels at home, and afterwards to vndertake vpon Paleſtine and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt; Then comming backe into Fraunce, make a new iourney into Affrick? yet found he at his entry to the Crowne, all his kingdome in trouble (neuer more quiet then at this preſent;) his Princes and great ones deuided from him, vnited againſt him, (which doe not deuiſe any thing now, but gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall vnion, and your ſeruice;) and did neuertheleſſe moſt happily ouercome all thoſe difficulties, his kingdome being not ſo great as yours by much, nor his renenue, the tenth part of that which you poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe. Do you thinke, Sir, that that braue Prince, which ſo valiantly vndertooke ſo great warres, as farre from his intereſt as from his limits, would haue demurred vpon the reuenge of ſo high an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury? Foraine examples would euen ſhame our owne, being ſo faire and ſo worthy of imitation; as among many, I cannot heere deny due place to one moſt famous and very neere our caſe. <hi>Philip</hi> of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon a great Captaine and a great king, as our eyes haue ſeen our great HENRY, hauing conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all
<hi>Greece,</hi> as he, Fraunce; is murthered, euen as he, in his own chiefe Citty, in a publick reioycing, and vpon the very inſtant when he was to execute the greateſt enterpriſe he euer had in hand. His ſonne
<hi>Alexander</hi> the great, yet a childe (for ſo <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthenes</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:12271:15"/>cals him) aſcended vpon the Throne of <hi>Philip</hi> as our LEWIS, vpon that of HENRY; but he feeles it ſhake vnder his feete; ſees
<hi>Greekes</hi> and <hi>Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> vp againſt him on euery ſide, his Counſell diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed wiſh him to leaue off the affaires of <hi>Greece,</hi> and quietly compound the reſt. Nay, ſaith he, but if I be perceiued to ſhrink at the beginning, I ſhall euer haue my hands full of them: and following this braue reſolution, ouer-throwes the <hi>Barbarians</hi> in a great battaile, ouer-runnes all <hi>Greece,</hi> like a fire, and deſtroyes the Empire of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt then in the world, with a ſmall Army of thirty thouſand men at the firſt, and a ſtocke of thirty Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents. Yet with ſo ſmall meanes neuer would goe out of the Hauen, but he would requite olde ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants and get newe; giuing all away ſaue hope, which he only kept for himſelfe: And when he had endeludged the world with a generall inundation of bloud, yet is not contented if <hi>Iupiter</hi> from heauen do not aſſure him, the death of his father is fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenged, and his <hi>Manes</hi> fully appeaſed.</p>
            <p>And you, Sir, who haue more Captaines, then he Souldiers; more Millions then he Talents; more ſtedfaſtnes in your eſtate, more obedience in your ſubiects, more loue in your Nobility, more wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in your Counſell, then euer <hi>Alexander</hi> had; with ſo many aduantages, wil you not reſolue your ſelfe to the execution of that vengeance? wil you not ſteele your ſelfe in that reſolution? and will you ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be faint-harted at this firſt tryal? will you winck at your Fathers murther? and tarry till another knife, forged (perhaps) vpon the ſame Anuile, ſend you
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12271:15"/>the ſame way, tell his dolefull <hi>Shadow,</hi> that for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning the reuenge of his death, you your ſelfe loſt your owne life? Oh! let me rather looſe mine eyes then ſee it, rather my ſenſes, rather my vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, rather all, then feele it, or at any time come to the knowledge thereof! This puts me out of frame, this kills me, when in the fit of this burning Ague, in the ſharpnes of this paine, thoſe who but yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day armed them ſelues for ſome Duch, come &amp; tell me now, we muſt not ſpeake of warr for the Kings death: for what els then Country-men? for a foote of ground, for <hi>Cleves,</hi> or <hi>Iuliers,</hi> which are none of ours?</p>
            <p>I neuer ſpoke of <hi>Naples, Millan,</hi> and <hi>Navarre,</hi> which are ours indeed; there they ſtand ſtil, &amp; there ſhal we euer find the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But where ſhall we recouer that great HENRY, who hath ben taken, &amp; ſo traiterouſly taken from vs? Yet if we had loſt him in war, where the heat of the fight ſpares none; Pacience; Armes are doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, &amp; oft-times number ſurmounts valour: But to haue him murthered in cold bloud, in a full peace, &amp; before the eyes of al the world; &amp; that we durſt not, and that we ſhould not reuenge it, it would be the ſhamfulleſt and greateſt diſhonour that euer hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto vs, to cover, darken, kill, &amp; bury for euer, the whole French name, and what-ſoever glorious we haue done heretofore. Moreouer, we do neuer ſo ſenſibly eſteeme of other mens loſſes, as of our owne; All thoſe peeces, were indeed loſt for vs, not by vs, they were taken from our Fathers vpon ſome colour of right, at leaſt right of warr, which as our <hi>Brennus</hi> was wont to ſay, is the moſt auncient and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall Law; The griefe thereof is paſt long ſince:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12271:16"/>But if any would encroch now but one foot of land vpon our Borders, in what an other ſort would we ſtirr for it, then for all thoſe kingdomes? And will wee not ſtirre for the death of our Kings? who woulde not without feare vnder-take againſt their ſacred liues, if wee valued them cheaper then their Lands? Yet haue wee a kinde of comfort in thoſe loſſes; they were ſo deerly ſolde, that the poſſeſſors dare not much boaſt of it: And ſhall we not make them pay more deerly for the priceleſſe life of our deere Prince? Shall they laugh it out to our faces, whilſt we ſit baſely weeping? And ſhall not their inſolency ſharpen our anger? O French-women, &amp; no more French men, if that might euer be reproched vnto vs! But now, what relation, what proporcion, of the loſſe of ſome land, to the loſſe of a King, and of ſuch a King as he was? Neuertheles, who knowes not but the leaſt of thoſe peeces, hath often ſet all Chriſtendome in fire and bloud, our Kings them-ſelues not ſparing their owne liues for them?</p>
            <p>Againe, I neuer ſpoke in the yong daies of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties raigne; Then we could not chooſe but great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be amazed at the greatnes, at the ſuddennes of our blow, and ſomwhat yeild to the fury of the ſtorme; Then were we rather to looke to aſſure our ſelues then to trouble others, rather to defend then to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile, and panting vnder the waight of our ruyne, take holde (as it were) for a time, of that hand that had drawen it vpon vs; as not knowing, or rather not ſeeming, or rather not ſtriving, to knowe our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. But now, ſince there is nothing to be appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12271:16"/>ſince in their loweſt degree of weakenes &amp; miſery, they had no further end then onely to take <hi>him</hi> away, eſteeming they had gotten enough, if we might but looſe <hi>him,</hi> as to
<hi>his</hi> perpetuall glory they feared <hi>him</hi> alone, more then all France beſides; or els thinking that he being gone, all things would go away after <hi>him,</hi> &amp; of themſelues be turned vpſide downe; Since it pleaſed God in his diuine mercy to confound their thoughts, ſhewing them, and vs, and all the world, that he can ſcourge and haue pitty, wound to death with one angry hand, hauing the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtill ready to apply the plaiſter, and againſt all hope, to heale; that he can kill and make aliue, bring downe to the graue and raiſe vp againe; ſince we are now as ſtrong, and as ſtrongly ſetled as euer in your fathers time, if not more; Why ſhould we not ſpeak boldly? Why ſhould we not point at our enemies with the finger, and call them by their owne names? Why ſhould we not goe, and yet more boldly fall vpon them all?</p>
            <p>There is no more doubt, no more difficulty, who hath forged that parricidious ſteele; we know, alas! now we know to much their doctrine and practiſe; and cannot ſay worſe againſt them then they haue written themſelues. <hi>Time was,</hi> and in King <hi>Henry</hi> the thirds time it was, when we feared only ſecret con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, priuate conferences, hidden chambers of Meditacion; All theſe works of darknes were as yet done in the darke, and could catch none but ſome weake and brain-ſicke ſoules. But now, <hi>Time is,</hi> that he that can tranſforme himſelf in an Angell of light, hath ſet an open ſchoole thereof, and ſent his black
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12271:17"/>Doctors, thorough all nations (more ſafely to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue) falſely carrying the ſweete name whoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they perſecute, becauſe when he put them out of hell he told them <hi>A Ieſu ite:</hi> Now it is publikely taught, and as a thirtenth article of faith, maintained and commanded to be added to the Creede, vnder paine of eternall damnation. And if we do not at laſt open our eyes, if wee doe not ſet our ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, if we let it coole any longer, and not put it downe in hot blood, <hi>Time ſhall neuer be</hi> nor ſo good, nor ſo fit, as it is now.
<hi>Mariana</hi> was the firſt who was bold to reduce it in art, and precepts, in three ſet bookes, <hi>De regis deſtructione;</hi> And though many, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as peſtilent as he, both of his owne nation and Society, both before and after him, haue written v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon that vnhappy ſubiect, as
<hi>Ribadeneyra, Toledo, Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencia, Vaſquez, Azor, Sa,</hi> and others; yet becauſe, with them, he that can worke moſt miſchiefe, is worthy of the higheſt title, this moſt vnworthy villaine ſhall goe in the fore-front, ſince he without them, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue any of them, or rather aboue all them, hath wrought moſt villany, and kild ſo great a King: That execrable monſter could not be borne very far from Affrick; And <hi>Indè prima mali labes.</hi> Yet, becauſe <hi>Spayne</hi> ſhall not be diſgraced alone, by breeding ſuch <hi>royall</hi> Dragons, ſuch venemous <hi>Baſiliskes,</hi> which kill not men ſimply but kings; not with their ſight (being not otherwiſe ſo reſolute, or religiouſly minded as to venture ſo neere) but with their breath only and a farre off; And whoſe infectious ſtinck can ſtill mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not during their liues onely, but a thouſand yeares after their death, very farre from thoſe old<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12271:17"/>Prophets, whoſe dead carkaſes did raiſe others to life: There is no Nation in the world, but hath a ſhare in the ſhame, <hi>Germany,</hi> euen honeſt
<hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> that golden <hi>Latium</hi> of old <hi>Saturnus,</hi> and who hath kept herſelfe more vnſpotted of this newer world, wil acknowledge ſhe hath no ſmall part ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; There you ſhall find one of thoſe, doting indeed, and yet no leſſe proud, &amp; yet no leſſe wicked, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, who dares not onely vomit his venome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt kings, but inueighing againſt them, vſurpe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen their very title and phraſe, as in a kinde of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, or as if he would play the king himſelfe; But oh! how farre commeſt thou ſhort, impudent <hi>Gret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerus?</hi> No
<hi>Iebuzit</hi> but one only <hi>Araunah</hi> could euer bring forth a
<hi>Royall Gift;</hi> and farre better hadſt thou done to keepe thy ſelfe within thine owne rancke, &amp; adding the moſt crooked letter of the Alphabet, and moſt like thy ſerpent-like dealing, to thy title, more fitly call it, <hi>Baſiliscon Doron.</hi> But God would not haue thee both wicked and wiſe at once; for when thou haſt broke thy head at the very head and firſt word of thy booke, it is not enough, but thou muſt needes break thy neck alſo in thy fooliſh dedication, to ſuch a one as thou neuer ſaweſt, to ſuch a one as thou ſhalt neuer ſee (for that great ſoule being departed penitent, no doubt, but where ſhe is, <hi>Gretzerus</hi> there ſhalt thou hardly come) finally, to ſuch a one as ſhall neuer heare of it; and if ſhe ſhould, could neuer but greatly abhorre to be cogged from heere below, &amp; perſwaded to make a party there aboue for the
<hi>Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oliſts,</hi> and Cabaliſe with the bleſſed Virgin, with S.
<hi>Brigid,</hi> S. <hi>Andrew</hi> (&amp; why not S. <hi>George</hi> to?) with a high<pb n="30" facs="tcp:12271:18"/>hand to carry from God ſuch things, as ſhe now vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> better information knowes moſt to be eſchew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Together &amp; of the ſame feather, you haue there one <hi>Becanus,</hi> the more wicked becauſe the more wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; ſo apt are theſe monſter-men to turne to ill vſes the very bleſſings of God. A little lower there is <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolus Scribanius,</hi> who moſt iuſtly aſhamed of his tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous name, hath ben faine to faine another in his <hi>Ample Theater of diſhonour,</hi> yet neuer forgetting herein the ambitious pride naturall to the ſociety, in taking of the beſt when they chooſe: One, who as though he were not able of himſelfe to be wicked e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, therein is he more wicked, that he praiſes the wickedeſt. <hi>Poland, Sweth-land, Tranſ-ſiluania, Bohemia,</hi> at their owne coſt, will contribute to the publicke ſhame, thoſe by whome they haue receaued, and ſtil receaue ſo much ſmart, though ſome haue paide deere enough for it. And after theſe farther coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, the remoteſt part of that famous Iland, <hi>penitus toto orbe remota</hi> will not be aſhamed to ſtake her peny (<hi>Haies</hi> and <hi>Hamilton</hi>) though not a peny worth, to the common reproch of Nations. But belike, her ſiſter would be too proud, if ſhe could not name for herſelfe, or rather againſt herſelfe, red-hatted, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther red-harted, <hi>Allens, Campion, Hart, Parſons, Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, Hall, Teſmond, Gerrard, Hammond,</hi> all bloody or fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery Traytors, and their ſuperior in all, <hi>Garnet.</hi> And now, Sir, among all them, perhaps you thinke your Fraunce will eſcape free; But alas! ſhall we not finde within our owne bowels, one <hi>Kakodemono-zannes,</hi> apoligiſing for this <hi>Garnet,</hi> and <hi>Franciſcus Verona</hi> for
<hi>Ian Chaſtell?</hi> both which, we know whence they are,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12271:18"/>but ſince they themſelues condemne their owne deeds, by counterfeiting their names, and therein (the onely thing they haue done well) in ſome ſort redeeme their Countries ſhame; let them dye for euer, vnknowne indeed and vnnamed; let thoſe that haue any part in them, diſclaime it; let them periſh in their blood, &amp; let me not haue their names within my lips. But oh! but we haue ſuch as glory in their owne infamy, thoſe curſed ones that call euil, good, and good, euill; who leaſt they and their villanies ſhould not be knowne enough by their writings, haue preached it openly, from Towne to Towne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the world, and ſhameleſſely taught it with a brazen face in their publicke leſſons; to ſhowe that Fraunce owes nothing to the reſt in treaſon &amp; wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes. But becauſe holy father <hi>Cotton</hi> was come of late, as it were with a blaſt of his ſweete breath, and in a ſheete of paper, to gaineſay and diſanull all his predeceſſors miſ-doings, and ſeeme to recouer the honor of the ſociety (though if his Amphibolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Equiuocations be rightly tryed, he ſpeakes as trayterouſly as any of them all) yet, leaſt they ſhould take to much hold of him, and interpret his double meaning in the better part; or rather to checke him as a falſe brother, &amp; one that had yeelded to much to the time; Behold, out of Italy the great
<hi>Iebuzit</hi> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaliſed, the great Cardinall ſhortly to be Papiſed; who not contented with that which he hath former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly written (as well he might, for any new thing hee ſayes) but becauſe it was onely done by the way, and among his other controuerſies (a load to big for any man to carry) comes out now, as the <hi>Triarij</hi> in that<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12271:19"/>great Army of forlorne hopes, with a booke by it ſelfe and of ſet purpoſe, ſounding and denouncing from the <hi>Vatican</hi> to al Princes, they are ſubiect to the Pope <hi>in temporalibus.</hi> True it is that in <hi>Atheus tOrtus</hi> that is, he himſelfe, had firſt made the way before him; but it was vnder an obſcure name, &amp; that could not carry great waight: But ſince the Chapleine was ſo bold, as to vndertake no leſſe then a great king for his ſhare, to write againſt; Do you thinke, Sir, that his
<hi>Illuſtriſſime,</hi> Lord and Maiſter, hath it againſt
<hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clay</hi> onely? No, no, poore <hi>Barclay</hi> is but the pooreſt part of his booke; yet his ſonne takes it in hand as his fathers cauſe; and, I am ſure, will not leaue the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall vnpaid. Neither is it againſt the king your braue father; They haue his hart faſt, and haue don as ſome Barbarians were wont; They haue executed him firſt, &amp; then comes forth this ſentence of death againſt him: But there is nothing more to be had of him, but your ſelfe; your ſelfe, Sir, It is againſt your ſelfe directly that this booke is written, againſt all kings aliue, againſt al kings yet vnborne; The haukes of a Cardinall, will not flie for leſſe, then at the birds of Paradice. And you, holy father, oh! is it after that maner you wil haue your ſons harts? Sure, ſure, that great father of mankind, of whom you pretend your ſelf ſo wrongfully to be the general Vicar, did neuer meane it ſo, when he ſaid, <hi>My ſon giue me thy hart.</hi> But you, ſweet childe, ſince you ſee two <hi>Barclaies,</hi> two pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate men, &amp; none of them a Proteſtant, nor nothing neere; the one, vndertake it ſo vertuouſly againſt the Pope, vpon no other particuler offence, but the meere loue of the truth; the other, follow it ſo duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12271:19"/>againſt Pope, Cardinall and all, onely as his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers quarrell, which yet is no ſuch matter; you, I ſay, which are ſo great, ſo noble, ſo auncient, and ſo mighty a king, will you not reuenge your fathers death? will you not reuenge your owne quarrel, againſt one that was but a Cardinall fiue yeares ago? one, that was but a baſe prieſt once? It is he, It is he, that ſpeakes in that booke, it is he that made it;
<hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin</hi> is vnworthy of your anger; He is but a meane inſtrument, he is but a ſlaue, and dares not do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then his maſter bids: The Pope himſelfe, the great Lord, the great God, of al, &amp; not
<hi>Acquaviva,</hi> a ſlaue too, hath viewed it, corrected it, allowed it, cauſed it to be printed at his owne charges, &amp; vnder his owne noſe, leaſt there ſhould be any fault in the print. To what end then, tarry any longer? what will you haue more? when they haue kild you alſo, you ſhal no more be able to take reuenge; Take it while you can, and while you may.</p>
            <p>Yet am not I of thoſe hot-burning ſpirits (though a ſtrong Proteſtant, I confeſſe) that would ſet Rome all in blood and fire; and dig vp her foundacions a thouſand fathomes vnder the ground. I would haue Rome reformed, not Rome ruyned. And what can the poore walls do withal for the inhabitants ſinnes? Yea, I will vnparcially deale with the Pope, and with more kindnes then he dares looke for at any Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants hand. Let euery Prince, according to the law of God, of Nature, and of Nations, eſtabliſh a good and holy Patriarch within his owne dominions, to whome all his Church men ſhall anſwer, &amp; to none els without, and he anſwer for them; Let the Biſhop<pb n="34" facs="tcp:12271:20"/>of Rome reduce himſelfe, or be reduced, to that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, wherein he was when the Councell of Nicea did graunt it him, and then let him haue the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of al our Patriarchs, as the ancienteſt; Let him keepe ſtill the keyes of his owne gates, as an eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Prince; yea and the ſword within his owne ſcabberd, as a ſecular Prince to; And let him draw it when he liſt, and flouriſh with it, in his owne territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. I am ſure this is the beſt, this is the ſhorteſt, way to reforme many abuſes, which the reaſonabler ſort auow are crept into the Churche; the ſurer way to reconcile that wilfull diuerſity of opinions, which hath ſo long diſtracted the harts and mindes, yea &amp; the bodies, of Frenchmen, into ſeuerall factions; bringing your two flocks againe into one folde, and vnder a ſhepheard of your owne: And there ſhall not be a
<hi>Huguenot</hi> in Fraunce.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Iebuzits</hi> (which I wil neuer grace with their vſurped name) If you will not deale with them, as all Chriſtian Princes did once, and at once, and vpon farr leſſer reaſons, with the poore knight-Templers: If you will not renew that wiſe ſentence of your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, pronounced againſt them with his own mouth, yet full of blood when they did beat out his teeth; &amp; rather imitate his hurtful clemency, that call'd them againe to ſtrike at his hart: If you wil not followe the laudable example of that graue Senat &amp; Common-wealth, whoſe Catholicity none can cal in queſtion: Then at leaſt, at leaſt, &amp; for a great worke of ſupere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation, &amp; tranſcendency of kindnes, let them be brought vnder a new General of our own Natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, let them take a new oath to him, he to your Patriacrh,<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12271:20"/>your Patriarch, to your ſelfe; &amp; ſo let it be ſeuerally through al Nations, without hauing any thing, either to medle or correſpond one with another.</p>
            <p>But Sir, the Tyrant is in ſuch &amp; ſo long a poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his vſurped power, as he will thinke theſe moſt equall conditions, vniuſt; and there is no hope of all this to take effect, without the ſword: If faire meanes would do it, the better; It is written
<hi>Beati pacifici,</hi> and moſt happy be they indeed. But if peace cannot be had with peace; If an vncertaine, but honorable, war be to be preferred to a certainly dangerous, but diſhonorable, peace; To the ſword then, in Gods name &amp; to the fire, if need be: And bleſſed, <hi>ô</hi> thrice-bleſſed be the war &amp; war-makers, whoſe end is, ſo happy &amp; deſired a peace. But all the fier that can euer be kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, all the blood we can euer ſhed, will not giue vs our king againe; True, but let vs be wiſe, after the blow at leaſt, ſince we haue receaued ſo mighty a one; That which can not bring back HENRY, may preſerue LEWIS; you ſhall make your own life ſure, by reuenging the death of your father; and yeeld vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whome you owe your ſelfe, the iuſtice you owe to all. So <hi>Ceſar</hi> made ſure his owne Statues by ſetting vp againe thoſe of
<hi>Pompey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if any crooked ſoule, or weake minde, will ſtill wilfully contend, that you are young, and your affaires engaged to other ends; Once more for all I aunſwer, whatſoeuer they be, they cannot, they muſt not, they ought not, to admit other or more conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient and neceſſary ends, then thoſe of your honor, life, and ſafety, wherein all ours is included, and with yours and ours, that of all Chriſtendome. For<pb n="38" facs="tcp:12271:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:12271:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:12271:22"/>your perſon, I haue ſhewed, you are great, both for your age, &amp; Kingdome, fauoured beſides of heauen and earth in ſo iuſt a quarrell; namely of other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces your good friends and neighbors, all touched in this murther.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p>KIng, you <hi>ô</hi> moſt mighty, moſt wiſe, moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, King of yonder fortunat Ilands, which by nature (as ſo many little worlds) moſt fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in themſelues, are yet more fortunate by your gouernment: Bright morning-ſtarre of humane learning, holy Oracle of heauenly wiſdome, puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied light of the fineſt and moſt refined iudgements; vnto whome there is not any crowned head at this day, liuing, but will &amp; muſt needs ſtoope in acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of ſuperiority; Thrice worthy Monarch, whoſe name I need not otherwiſe ſet downe, ſince euen thoſe that moſt are loath, muſt needs acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge you by your own marks. Do you not really, &amp; feelingly lament for our loſſe? Do you not aboue all take it in deed as your owne? Haue I not often heard you tel it to others? Haue you not often told it to my ſelfe? Alas! &amp; ſo very wel you may; Our braue father your deare brother was taken but in exchange; It was but his lot to goe before; The enemies did, &amp; yet at this time do, pretend no leſſe againſt your life. You knowe it of olde by the bleſſed miſcarrying of their helliſh plots; and you knew it of late, euen by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who more carefull of his friends ſafety then of his owne (as though he had done enough to warne you) was ſince negligent in garding himſelfe: Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, o double Monarch, equally ouer ſoules, by
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12271:22"/>that worth which makes you a king, thogh you had not ben borne ſo, as ouer bodies by right of blood: Time is now paſt writing; forbearance, longanimity, clemency, pardon, and all pen-worke are now out of ſeaſon: the ſword, the ſword muſt cut the knots of this buſines. They make themſelues worthy to write againſt you, who are moſt vnworthy you ſhould looke vpon them: And while you ſtriue to cut their taile, contrary to the weakeſt Serpents, their venom lies in the head. They get a name by being ouer-come by ſo famous an Aduerſary, and yet liue. They dare bite you againe, they dare ruffle your honor, who were better to be ruffled by a hangman, a moſt fit decyder of their quarrels. Alarum, Alarum, Hee himſelfe hath throwen into the <hi>Tiber</hi> his moſt lawful weapons (as too kinde) ſetting all his reſt vpon <hi>Pauls</hi> ſword, but S. PAVLS ſword, euen that ſword of the ſpirit is ours, and will not cut for him. His ſword is but vaine imaginary, blunt, broken, borrowed, though very hurtfull. Yours is your owne, euen the royall, euen the reall, and ſharp ſword of the iuſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge of God, which ſhall breake his aſunder like brittle glaſſe: and that ſcepter of yron, which the ſonne of the Almighty hath put into your hands, ſhall cruſh his in pieces, as a Potters veſſell. On, on, ſword againſt ſword, let's try which cuts beſt.</p>
            <p>Euen the greateſt, euen the beſt part of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, &amp; all the honeſt Catholicks &amp; not papiſts wil followe you; who looke for nothing els but to ſee ſomebody in the field to break the firſt yce. Now they grieue, now they are aſhamed, to haue bene ſo long nuſled vp in ſo many groſſe errors, now they confes<pb n="38" facs="tcp:12271:23"/>them; now they begin to ſee ſomewhat cleere; and where they had of old an Aegiptian darknes before their eies, they haue now but cobweb-lawnes, which yet God will remoue in his good time. Long ſince haue many great &amp; learned men, earneſtly long'd for reformation in their owne Church; who yet affirme they cannot hope for ſo great a good, vnleſſe the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of Rome (for ſo they ſticke not to call it) be put downe. And I might name a great perſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, a true Catholike, Apoſtolike, and not Roman, of whoſe worth, and great vertue, not only his owne country, to whome it hath ben moſt bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall, but euen Germany, Italy, Flanders, and by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection, Spaine, finally England it ſelfe, takes an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable notice of, with whome talking not long ago after a free opening of the ſoares of their Church, (which he could not well conceale, otherwiſe hee would) he tolde me a common ſaying of his, to ſhew how freely and honeſtly ſoeuer he acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the ſimple truth, he is not crackt in his own be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe and religion, That he thankes God with all his hart, that hauing had great dealings at <hi>Rome &amp; Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neua,</hi> and great friends of both ſides, yet God hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer kept him, in that trueſt &amp; ſureſt middle, that he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was a good Catholike &amp; nor a
<hi>Huguenot</hi> or a <hi>Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guer.</hi> I anſwered him, good my lord, oh! would to God we were all catholiks, after your faſhion: &amp; for me, if I were borne ſo, I would ſcarce beleeue I could change my religion for a better.</p>
            <p>Come then, come out, moſt noble king, come out by ſo much the ſooner as you ſee the matter eaſy; you haue ſo many men &amp; ſo many meanes; you are the<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12271:23"/>only Monarch in the world, who can ſet vp as many &amp; as good, both horſe &amp; foot, of his owne ſubiects, without begging ſupply, either of Albanians or Ruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, of Landsknechts or Suytzers. And yet, need you not much trouble your ſelfe; you need not ſtirre out of your royall Whitehall; There we wil ſend you the newes of the ruine of your Enemies: Your arms are long enough to chaſtiſe them all a farre off; moſt eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially your right Arme, the ſonne of your thigh, the flower of your ſtrength, the excellency of your dignity and power. Let's but haue him, let him but haue himſelfe, and he will come to vs; let him goe for the publique good of all Chriſtendome, for your intereſt, for his owne: We haue none elſe to be the head of our <hi>Croiſado.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p>ANd you, young Sunne, ryſing to all glory and happynes, hope of the earth, ioy of the ſea, eye of the world, wonder of mindes, loue of harts, ſweet comfort and delight of mankinde; my moſt noble, my moſt braue Prince, all hart; God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid I ſhould forbid learning, and leſſe in a Prince then in any priuate man, and where it may eaſily be gotten without hinderance to further and more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary ends. But thus much I dare ſay, with their good leaue, who are more wiſe then I; As times ſtand now, as vrgent occaſions require, you are lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned enough for a Prince; and if any Prince in the world euer had leſſe need of learning it is your ſelfe:
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12271:24"/>you ſhall neuer want it, as long as you giue vp your ſelf wholy to be ruld, as a ſecond wheele, as an inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or Globe, by that firſt Motor, by that heauen of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, by that matchles Father of yours, which hath learning enough for you both. And let it not grieue you needs to yeeld vnto him in that kinde; It is a wonder ſcarce ſeen in many ages, to ſee a king lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, a wonder that was neuer ſeen but once, to ſee a king ſo learned as he. Our great and our firſt <hi>Fraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi> had ſcarce more learning then you, and yet did not leaue to be a great king, &amp; yet did not leaue to be called the great father and reſtorer of learning. And that great Prince alſo for whome we now mourne, was he not a great Captaine &amp; a great King, though not a great Scholler? True it is, he euer fauoured true learning where he found it, without any acception of perſons, no not of his rebells if they would be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled. And euen in his latter daies (greedy of
<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polloes</hi> bayes, as of the palmes of <hi>Mars</hi>) had he not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken (I dare ſay, by the Councell of a great Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall, for all Cardinals are not <hi>Iebuzits</hi>) to build in euery Citty a great Colledge and free-ſchoole for all kinde of learning; and to that end hire and gather to himſelfe all the famous learned men of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? Which royall deſigne our wiſe Queene now moſt aduiſedly following, there is a mighty great one already building in <hi>Paris,</hi> which, euen by antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, ſome call the <hi>Cut-throte of Ieſuits.</hi> It is enough for a Prince (though otherwiſe not ſo extreamely learned himſelfe) if onely he fauor learned men; and ſo he ſhall be ſure neuer to want learning at his need. Once more, farr be it from my thoughts, to diſwade<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12271:24"/>learning in a Prince, I know he can ſcarce fauor lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, if he haue no learning himſelfe; And great <hi>Alexander</hi> with his braue
<hi>Grecians,</hi> great <hi>Ceſar</hi> with his braueſt <hi>Romans,</hi> tell me, the Souldier who hath it and manages it well, hath a more eaſy, a more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, a more ready way, and a greater aduantage o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him that hath it not, to be a better Soldier; the Captaine, a valianter Captaine; the Prince, a greater Prince. But that it is not ſo eſſentially indiuiduall, &amp; vnſeparably incident to a King, as without a great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance thereof, he cannot be a great king indeed, and truly performe the duties of his great charge, It is onely that which I ſtand vpon; A thing whereof the contrary hath ben ſeen in euery age; And our owne fathers, and we our ſelues, can yet remember the ſame.</p>
            <p>Do not therefore mold any longer among your bookes, no not among your tiltings and fained com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats, though otherwiſe in peace, honorable, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull, needfull; To horſe, to horſe, the quarter is broken, the bloody Trumpet hath ſounded; True &amp; mortall warre is open. They haue killed your valo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous God-father, who miſſed to kill your ſelfe; yea euen him who by mutual agreement was appointed to be your ſecond father by your firſt, if the vnhappy blow had lighted vpon him: ſo aſſured were theſe two great Princes, &amp; greater friends, that their liues were ſought. It is time, it is high time to put on your Armour, and make your Enemies and ours, iuſtly to feele the ſmart which ſo much they feare, and by ſo vniuſt meanes ſeeke to preuent. Our young LEWIS will not be long after you, and though he can not<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12271:25"/>yet accompany you hand in hand, (as he would, if we would let him) in the thickeſt throng of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, to ſcatter and ouerthrow them, both vpon a couple of their beſt Gennets, both in like Armor, both in huge mighty feathers, all blacke with their burnt blood at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming out of the battell, white before for your mutuall loue and faith; yet he wil not be farre off, He will viſit you in your Campe if need be; And will euen glory and ioy, to lend his tender hand to gird your ſword when you goe out, meete you on horſebacke when you come in, bring you victorious vnder your Tent againe, and weeld your bloody ſword after the battell, as if he thought by that to enter into part of your glory, as the profit muſt needs be common.</p>
            <p>The noble preſidents of your royall Ancetors, yea in the very time of their thickeſt darkenes ought to moue you. Do you not amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g many heare the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty voice of that braue <hi>Coeur de Lyon,</hi> a French man by father and mother, and the firſt Prince, orderly born Engliſh, ſince the conqueſt? How ſtrongly doth he call vpon you? How farre went he to conquer the holy land? How many daungers, how many trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, how many paines, did he paſſe and ouercome? But now, ſince it is Gods pleaſure, the holy land is by two third parts neerer then it was then; A moſt fit, a moſt holy, a moſt eaſy ſubiect of your conqueſt. And wil you not take the croſſe on you to go thither, now in this ſhining brightnes of the Goſpell? There is no more a doe but go and take poſſeſſion. And what land now in the world, more <hi>ſacer,</hi> more holy, then holy Rome, which hath ben ſo much watred<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12271:25"/>by ſo much holy blood of ſo many Saints and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs? Behold, and why els doth ſhee call herſelfe <hi>Romala Santa,</hi> he <hi>Padre Santo,</hi> or his holynes?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p>GReat men, if you be but, men &amp; not worthy of a higher title, whoſe braines harbor ſo much wiſdome; whoſo breaſts, ſo much temperance, iuſtice &amp; faithfulnes, vertues ſo rare now adaies, any<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where els; which haue wrought in the world the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miracles of theſe latter times; fauorits of heauen, ſpirits of lead, of braſſe, of hard ſteele, purer then the very gold, ſeauenty times refined in the fornace; who (as it were) fetching euery yeare, by thouſands, whole ſhips laden with a new wiſedome out of <hi>India,</hi> are wiſer then their auncient
<hi>Gymnoſophiſts:</hi> you that ſhaking off a moſt cruell, and yet more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt yoke, are riſen from a baſe and ſeruile bondage, now to be equall with Princes, by your owne hands making your ſelues ſuch as you would be, &amp; ſetting a moſt lawfull bound to your high deſires (as though anything beſides your ſelues were not worth your ambition) were contented to haue but your owne ſelues; Generous <hi>Helots,</hi> farr better and more noble then your proud <hi>Lacedemonians.</hi> If euer you did kindely and faithfully helpe vs at our neede; If euer our great king did Kindly, faithfully, and gratefully, helpe you againe at yours, if vertue liue euen after death, and a loyall loue grounded vpon the ſame to ſo royall a friend: Come, come, ioyne hands with vs; Our caſe, our cauſe is your owne; your ſtrong bull worke, the Rampier of Chriſtendome, hath ben moſt vnluckily throwen downe; Ere it be long, the<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12271:26"/>enemy will giue you a furious, if not trecherous, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault. And euen though you would, though you could, forbeare loue to others, yet ſhew now your wiſdome for your ſelues, if euer you had any. You al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo peereles couple of Princely bretheren, both flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing in age, much more in worthy and warlike deeds; you great, not Citty-razer, as the other was, but Citty-rayſer, ſtrong
<hi>Neſtor,</hi> wiſe <hi>Aiax,</hi> the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of armes, the loue of Souldiers; now without controuerſie the firſt Captaine in the world: your taske is not yet at an end: To the field, to the fire, to the ſword once more, as glorious as I haue ſeen you many times; the ſicknes is more ſharp then euer, it is in relaps. And you martial <hi>Henry, Henry,</hi> doth not your hart riſe, at that great name? Doe you not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber who gaue it you? as though our great HENRY would not grace with it other then great Princes, and ſuch as he fore-knew, would be moſt worthy of the ſame.
<hi>Henry,</hi> if yet you remember his perſonall kindnes to you;
<hi>Henry,</hi> if yet you haue a drop of French blood, of that right noble blood of that high: Admirall your Grandfather, in his time the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of Captaines: And after theſe high reſpects, if priuate ones may take place, If yet you reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber theſe innocent plaies, but ſtill ſauouring of warre or lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, wherby we were wont to recreate and ſtirr vp your minde, while you were a childe; If yet you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member your many promiſes, ſo kindly made to me ſince you are a man; Vp, vp, I lay downe al particular pretentions, I claime all for the publique; Come &amp; auenge the death of your royall God-father, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, remember your owne father was killed ſo: And
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:12271:26"/>that a trayterous murtherer euen before you ſaw, did for euer bereaue you of the ſight of that moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Prince, who had giuen you the power of ſeing; and whome to haue ſeen, ſo many eyes would haue thought themſelues moſt happy.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p>IMperiall Princes, right honeſt <hi>Sycambrians,</hi> our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Bretheren, from whome when we departed, with dint of ſword to get vs a new habitation, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py we, if we had not left our integrity &amp; plainenes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde, or rather had kept aſwel as you, that which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed we brought with vs! Happy ſoules, bleſſed rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the golden age, if euer you pittied our hard caſe, who thinking to conquer other mens lands, loſt our owne mindes, and were ouercome euen by thoſe we ouercame; If there remain in you any ſpark of that ancient loue which once made vs all <hi>Germans,</hi> when we liued vnder the ſame heauen: But if old re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects ſerue not, if that feruent loue our moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King did ſo lately witnes vnto you, who ſet vp ſo great an army, endangered his whole eſtate, ventured his owne life, loſt it, euen in your quarrell, and for your ſakes; if the help we brought you at ſo fit a time, if the neuer enough lamented damage we ſuffer yet, and ſhall ſuffer longer, for your occaſion, can be of ſome effect in your noble harts: Come, come, and let vs all gather, as one man, to reuenge our common loſſe, &amp; preuent the common euill; for though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe the loſſe muſt ſtill be of our ſide, yet looke how much your deareſt honour remaines ingaged<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12271:27"/>therein. And you braue
<hi>Erneſt of Brandenburgh,</hi> Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prince, whoſe princely aſpect told me once you were ſuch, when moſt you would haue hid it, and for your better concealement, made me an hundred times ſit at the vpper end of your table, while I told you as often, I was ſcarce good enough to waite at it: Neuertheles did it, though with a willing kinde of ſhame and vnwillingnes, when you commaunded me once for all, it muſt needs be ſo. If euer you loued our nation in generall, If euer moſt eſpecially you admired, and proteſted affection to that hart-raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing Prince, as many times as I brought you to the ſight of him, as a priuate Gentleman, If euer you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated at night with loue and paſſion, that which you heard, that which you ſaw of him that day: <hi>Erneſt,</hi> I earneſtly beſeech,
<hi>Erneſt,</hi> I earneſtly adiure you, And with you, and in you, and by you, all your moſt noble houſe, and thoſe of your princely name, Come out to reuenge the publique iniury; And let me ſee you at the fore-front of our
<hi>Croiſade;</hi> No Princes haue ſuch an intereſt in this quarrell, nor among them, any ſo much as your ſelfe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p>VVOrthily worthy, and all praiſe-worthy <hi>Heroes,</hi> True remnant of thoſe old euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuing <hi>Troians,</hi> who inuincible to all force, had neuer dyed, if ſubtilty and treaſon, the worſe, becauſe masked with Religion, had not ſurpriſed their ſimply-honeſt ſoules, and ſooner burn'd their bodies, then ouercome their mindes;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:12271:27"/>you that now trenched within your owne waters, (as it were for feare of an other ſuch accident) where alſo neuer any body could come to hurt you, no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy can; And euen when that great Deluge of the
<hi>Gothes</hi> ſpred it ſelfe round about you, were left to your ſelues, ſafely ſwimming in your land-no-land, or rather ſo many Ilands; Sacred
<hi>Ephores,</hi> ſharp-ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Areopagits,</hi> graue Senate, who not to haue one King, ſubiect in a deadly ſtroke to wound all his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, haue a Prince, as it were in name only, but are ſo many Kings your ſelues, and Kings indeed, ſince you commaund Kingdomes; which yet you ſhould command in no leſſe quantity, then once that aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Monarcichall Common-wealth, (a part of your Type) ſeeing your <hi>MarTial</hi> power, is no leſſe then theirs, if your <hi>Marcial</hi> equitie had not made you as moderate, as they were greedy; Truly ſonnes of <hi>Mars</hi> in deed, for valour; Truly children of <hi>Marc,</hi> for piety; and againe, of
<hi>Mercury,</hi> for induſtry &amp; riches. If euer you remember that auncient alyance between both our States, If euer you remember the recent loue &amp; true friendſhip of the <hi>fourth</hi> his offers &amp; endeauours to you, and for you, when the <hi>third</hi> and the <hi>fift</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to plott your ruyne; If you haue, euen of late, felt the ſharpe ſtings of that Tyrannicall ambition; ſeen and felt trayterous murthers within your own bowels, though not againſt your King (when you haue none) yet againſt your beſt men, and thoſe that moſt ſoundly haue maintayned your Kingly autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; If the innocent wounds, of that learned wiſe, and good <hi>Padre Paolo,</hi> yet aliue in ſpight of their hart; If the holy aſhes, yet almoſt hot, of that happy<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12271:28"/>martyr, your worthy
<hi>Fulgentio,</hi> burned in yonder hilly Citty, for that quarell, though vpon other farr fetched, fayned and moſt falſe pretences; If the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all blood of your greateſt, of your beſt friend, crye yet aloud <hi>Vengeance, Vengeance,</hi> in your eares: Come, come, braue and wiſe men, ſhake hands with ſo many and ſo great Princes, Be none of the laſt to take the Croſſe on you; The matter is of State, not of Religion: And let not that ſtaine, for the firſt time, be caſt on your ſpotles name, that you once forſooke your friends, euen fighting for your quarel, as much as for theirs; that you once forſooke your owne ſelues. And when was ſuch a thing euer ſeen, either in you or others? Come, come, I ſay, you ſhall be ſtill as good Catholicks, as you were afore, if not better; They tremble already for feare, They are ours; And though they cannot ſtand againſt vs, and though (thanks be to God) we haue no need of more help, hauing equitie, ſtrength, valour, riches, and all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantages of our ſide, yet we call, yet we ſummon you, not to exclude you of your part of the glory.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to the you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g King of Fraunce.</note>NOw Sir, if any will yet grudge, ſaying, I take to much vpon me, and that yourſelfe and all thoſe great Princes are wiſe, &amp; ready enough in that which concerneth them, without neede ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of my counſell or ſummoning. Firſt I ſay, I pray God, in this ſence, I may be a needles
<hi>Herald</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and you gather your ſelues without calling, though otherwiſe truth be euer truth, well beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12271:28"/>and to be followed, in any mans mouth. For the reſt, I am neither a Councellor, nor worthy to be ſo, but a ſilly worme, and poore Soldier as once I was, I am a piece, not only of your State, but of the Chriſtian Common-wealth; and as a feeling (though vnprofitable) member of that great bodie, intereſſed in the loſſe of ſo excellent and needfull a head: by ſo much the more as I euer preferred the publike good, before my priuate welfare; the honor of my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, before my perticular aduancement; and the life of my Soueraigne and of all good Chriſtian Kings, aboue mine owne, &amp; all others of my neereſt &amp; dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt kindred: who yet being already croſſe-ſigned, and the leaſt of an hundred thouſand which are ready to croſſe-ſigne themſelues for ſo lawfull and ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall a cauſe, when either by this my ſummoning, or ſome other more effectuall meanes, I ſee a iuſt army in the field, am moſt ready to embrace againe my auncient profeſſion, which I had forſworn; to ſcowre my old weapons, ruſty with our
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ong peace, which I thought neuer to vſe againe; And taking in hand my ſharpeſt ſpeare of all, moſt boldly venture my life, as farr as any; moſt happy to be loſt in this quarrell, the right quarrell of God and Gods annoynted.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>
            <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
         </trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
